<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title> - Calyx Blog</title>
	<link href="https://capra.cs.cornell.edu/calyx/post/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://capra.cs.cornell.edu/calyx/post/"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2021-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://capra.cs.cornell.edu/calyx/post/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Growing an Open-Source Hardware Infrastructure</title>
		<published>2021-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2021-07-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link href="https://capra.cs.cornell.edu/calyx/post/one-year/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://capra.cs.cornell.edu/calyx/post/one-year/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been roughly one year since the submission of the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;rachitnigam.com&#x2F;files&#x2F;pubs&#x2F;calyx.pdf&quot;&gt;original Calyx
paper&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
In that time, we’ve continued building tons of new tools, frontends, and
integrations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simplifying-the-hardware-workflow&quot;&gt;Simplifying the Hardware Workflow&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calyx is a compiler infrastructure that needs to interact with frontends
(languages that generate Calyx IR) and backends (mechanisms to run Calyx
generated code).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple workflow that goes from &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;capra.cs.cornell.edu&#x2F;dahlia&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dahlia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (a C-like frontend) to simulation
through &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.veripool.org&#x2F;verilator&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Verilator&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; involves tediously running several commands.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;# Generate Calyx IR from Dahlia
% dahlia&amp;#x2F;fuse -b calyx --lower -l error -o out.futil
# Generate Verilog from Calyx IR
% calyx&amp;#x2F;futil -b verilog out.futil -o out.sv
# Compile Verilog using Verilator
% verilator -cc --trace out.sv --exe testbench.cpp \
  --exe --build --top-module main
# Execute the generated Verilator code.
% .&amp;#x2F;Vmain   # Execute the Verilator model
&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, every time there is change in the input Dahlia file, all of the
commands need to be re-executed.
It’s easy to see why getting into hardware design can be so daunting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to provide a seamless command-line tool that makes it easy for
novices to use and interact with hardware design tools, we built &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;capra.cs.cornell.edu&#x2F;docs&#x2F;calyx&#x2F;fud&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;fud&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Fud is built around the idea of “stages” which provide a way for transforming
a set of input files (say a Dahlia source file) into output files (say a file
with Calyx IR).
Fud can also chain sequences of stages to transform files several times.
For example, the following &lt;code&gt;fud&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; command runs all the necessary steps to
compile a Dahlia source file through Calyx and simulate it with Verilator:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;% fud exec input.fuse --from dahlia --to verilog
&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fud also makes it easy to switch between outputs making debugging at different
levels a breeze:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;% fud exec input.fuse --from dahlia --to calyx
&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool is written in python and can be easily extended to support more
frontends and backends.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;calyx-on-fpgas&quot;&gt;Calyx on FPGAs&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our original paper on Calyx ran Vivado’s place and route tool to gather
resource usage estimates.
Since then, we’ve put in the effort to get Calyx generated designs running on
real FPGA boards.
This represents an exciting step towards realizing Calyx as an infrastructure
for rapid development of domain-specific languages that generate hardware
designs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to support Xilinx FPGAs, we implemented an AXI interface so that host
programs can communicate with kernels running on an FPGA.
We wrote a interface wrapper in Verilog that translates AXI commands into the &lt;code&gt;go&#x2F;done&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;
style interface that Calyx components expect as well as copies memory into
local BRAMs that Calyx components can access them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Xilinx tools require several different metadata files alongside the Verilog
source.
We automated the creation of these files with &lt;code&gt;fud&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to make interacting with
these tools more seamless.
The only piece of the puzzle that is manual at the moment is writing OpenCL
host code to integrate the kernel into an application.
While we are not looking to completely automate writing the host code, we would
like to write a generic host that understands the same data format we use for
simulation to enable easier validation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we are able to support the specific Xilinx boards, we do not yet have a
general solution.
A missing piece in the puzzle is a generic interface and intermediate
representation that can target arbitrary boards.
Thankfully, our collaborators at the University of Washington have been
developing &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;vegaluisjose&#x2F;reticle&quot;&gt;exactly this&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-frontends&quot;&gt;New Frontends&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calyx’s development as a language and an infrastructure is driven by frontends
that make use of it.
Since the publication of our paper, we have implemented two new frontends that
can be used to stress test Calyx.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tvm-relay&quot;&gt;TVM Relay&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;apache&#x2F;tvm&quot;&gt;TVM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a compiler for machine learning frameworks that can optimize and
target kernels to several different backends.
Our TVM frontend compiles TVM’s internal IR, called Relay, to Calyx IR, and
can successfully simulate small neural networks.
Relay instructions are quite high-level, implementing operators such as a
two-dimensional convolution.
In order to side-step manually generating such operators in Calyx and to
simplify debugging, we instead generate Dahlia programs to implement these
operators.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cucapra&#x2F;calyx&#x2F;pull&#x2F;504&quot;&gt;Calyx #504&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, we successfully
simulated a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;LeNet&quot;&gt;LeNet&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; network model.
Of course LeNet is an extremely simple neural network and our long-term goal
is to support modern networks.
Our next target is the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;neurohive.io&#x2F;en&#x2F;popular-networks&#x2F;vgg16&#x2F;&quot;&gt;VGG&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; network.
However, we’ve also realized while building this network that simple,
Verilator-based simulation is going to be too slow so we’re also working
on other efforts like running Calyx on an FPGA and building a fast simulator
for Calyx itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;number-theoretic-transform-ntt&quot;&gt;Number Theoretic Transform (NTT)&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number theoretic transform (NTT) is a generalization of the fast Fourier
transform, commonly used as a primitive in homomorphic cryptography.
We implemented an NTT pipeline generator produces the NTT transform of some
input with the provided bit width and input array size parameters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;calyx-circt&quot;&gt;Calyx + CIRCT&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;llvm&#x2F;circt&quot;&gt;CIRCT&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (Circuit IR Compilers and Tools) is a cross-community effort to build
an open-source hardware ecosystem using the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mlir.llvm.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MLIR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; framework.
The MLIR framework represents compilation as a series of transformations between
“dialects” or languages at different levels of abstractions.
In the long-term, the CIRCT community is interested in compiling high-level
languages to hardware designs, which is something Calyx can already do today.
In order to align our efforts, we’ve started implementing a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;llvm&#x2F;circt&#x2F;tree&#x2F;46ae6df8eb30c0404a0cc54f92a68a63ef643c89&#x2F;test&#x2F;Dialect&#x2F;Calyx&quot;&gt;Calyx dialect&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
which can be emitted from other dialects in CIRCT, transformed by the Calyx compiler,
and of course, integrated with &lt;code&gt;fud&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;control-directed-optimizations-register-unsharing&quot;&gt;Control-Directed Optimizations: Register Unsharing&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calyx’s strength is in its ability to represent &lt;em&gt;both&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the structure and the
control flow of a hardware accelerator.
Apart from simplifying the design of frontends, this also enables unique
new optimizations that we’ve termed control-directed hardware optimizations.
These optimizations are truly unique to Calyx—the compiler needs to have
both an understanding of the control flow and the structural representation
to implement them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such optimization is register unsharing.
Yes you read that right, &lt;em&gt;unsharing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. But please hold your ire for a moment, I
promise there is a method to my madness.
In compilers like LLVM (and Calyx), register allocation (or register
sharing) passes aim to reduce the usage of registers in a hardware design.
Owing to the multi-objective design space, certain hardware designs, such as
ones targeting FPGAs may want to do the opposite—use more registers in
order to simplify other circuitry.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharing reduces the resources a given design requires; however, it does so at
the cost of increasing the wiring complexity.
Each “shared” instance of a register requires a multiplexer (or a mux) to arbitrate
access to it.
Unsharing, in contrast, moves the trade-off in an opposite direction. It
increases the number of registers in a design but reduces the wiring
complexity by requiring fewer multiplexers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no universally “correct” places on this trade-off curve. FPGAs have a
set amount of resources per block and so up to a certain point it can be better
to have more registers rather than more multiplexers while the opposite holds for
taping out a design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cucapra&#x2F;calyx&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;calyx&#x2F;src&#x2F;passes&#x2F;register_unsharing.rs&quot;&gt;optimization pass&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; itself uses a Calyx-specific version
of a reaching definitions analysis that accounts for Calyx’s guarded
assignments.
The reaching definition can be used to calculate groups that “must-write” and
“may-read” to registers and use this information to rewrite groups to unshare
registers.
For more technical details about the implementation please take a look at the
&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cucapra&#x2F;calyx&#x2F;pull&#x2F;511&quot;&gt;pull request&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;calyx-interpreter&quot;&gt;Calyx Interpreter&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major infrastructure tool that’s been under-development is a native
interpreter for Calyx. It might seem a bit strange to be working on an
interpreter given that Calyx already has a compiler; typically language
development starts with an interpreter and moves to a compiler later as they are
far more efficient. Nevertheless, a Calyx interpreter represents an exciting
development for the Calyx ecosystem allowing us to address many different
problems: from reducing simulation complexity to verifying compiler passes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the primary way to quickly run Calyx code is by compiling it
to Verilog and using &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.veripool.org&#x2F;verilator&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Verilator&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to simulate it.
In process, however, we end up losing all of the control information represent
in the original Calyx program which can be used to optimize simulation.
We expect that by using the higher-level control information information in
the Calyx program, we can improve simulation speeds by an order of magnitude.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common problem in circuit simulation is that a
large portion of the circuit is not running at any given time but still must be
simulated. There are many clever heuristics for identifying the dormant parts of
the design and saving time by not simulating them; however Calyx needs no such
heuristics. The control structure in Calyx code means that we know precisely
what parts of the design are running at any given moment and needn’t waste time
simulating portions of the circuit which are known to be dormant.
Furthermore, Calyx IR itself has less simulation complexity than the RTL it
generates.
Since the information available at the IR level is more structured, the
simulation itself is free of the complex details that appear at the RTL layer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Calyx interpreter will let us develop a better debugging infrastructure
with support for traditional tools like breakpoints, pausing execution, and
dumping internal state.
Today, when designing debuggers for hardware, developers have to trade-off between
the fast but opaque simulation on FPGAs or slow but transparent simulation in
software simulation.
A Calyx interpreter represents the best of both worlds, enabling faster and
transparent execution.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final note, a simulator is also a boon both for the language itself and the
core compiler infrastructure. Being able to run Calyx programs directly means we
can perform differential testing on compiler passes and verify that the given
changes made by a pass are indeed semantic preserving with respect to the input
program. Plus, the act of making the interpreter itself is an excellent way of
“hardening” the semantics of the language as it requires making clear decisions
on corner cases obscured by the translation to Verilog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any of these directions excite you, or you’re just interested in using
Calyx as a backend, please &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener nofollow noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;cucapra&#x2F;calyx&#x2F;discussions&quot;&gt;reach out to us&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;! We’d love hear
from you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
